Vante as a spiritual practitioner
despite dedicating years to cultivating
Good Will towards
others I still find occasional moments
of ill will
surfacing while I maintain Faith In My
Chosen technique I'm starting starting to feel
technique I'm starting starting to feel
fatigued by its repetitive nature may
you be well may be
happy just imagining
uh Goodwill and spreading it to others
so I'm curious if there's an alternative
approach to sending Goodwill to others
that could rejuvenate my practice and
Infuse it with new
energy uh
no there is no alternative way of
sending anything to
others so the only way to not act out of
will will is
to it's not through through through
fabric deating love towards others and
pasting it over the basis of ill will
the basis of irritation the basis of
greed aversion and distraction it's only
the only way to truly have U
friendliness towards others in an
unshakable manner is if you have
uprooted the basis for non-f
friendliness for greed for aversion for
distraction so the you're closer to
practicing meta rightly I must have said
this before um if you you're learning if
you're if you're basically becoming able
if you're developing a skill of not
acting out of your emotions by Body by
speech and mentally as well than by by
hundreds of years of spent of of
spreading Good Will thoughts and love
towards others that's just just like applying a
others that's just just like applying a
Band-Aid to to an infected wound without
having the slightest notion of how to
actually treat the infection just hoping
that the bandaid will will extinguish
the inflammation but it won't people
make it worse cuz it's Brewing
underneath cuz the circumstances you
know it can seem like it's working like
having thoughts and wishing people well
this your circumstances are you're
probably living in an environment you're
not starting arguments things are quite
calm so you're not getting angry you
don't not in a circumstances which are
inviting of arguments basically well
yeah are you not are you not getting
angry because the mind is immovable
by the thoughts of irritation or are you
not getting angry because there's
currently nothing annoying you but if
there were something you would not be
able to not get
angry um
so like it's not it's not a like you you
can have good thoughts and think loving
kindness of people if you want to make a
practice out of that just don't confuse
it for the practice of meta don't
confuse it for the practice of uprooting
the ill will because it isn't if you
just want to spend your day thinking
nicely about people that's fine there's
no problem with it the problem is when
you think that those those practices
those fabricated thoughts would somehow
magically uproot the the the liability
to ill will and irritations and
resistance that it's not about it does
not uh exist U on the level of other
people the root of ill will is the root
of resistance towards your own physical
presence and the feeling that's felt
there so paa that the Su talk about the
resistance towards your own feeling if
it's unpleasant that's the root of ill
will everything else is second to
it so the whole practice of
friendliness is as as basically as like
the U the sutas described very often
it's like having purified your behavior
way beforehand established in virtue
beforehand established in virtue
established in Right View established in
not acting out then you review the
beginning the core here is there any
resistance here no okay I will cultivate that
here no okay I will cultivate that
framework nonresistance towards anything
that arises here on the level of feeling
within this
experience then I shall direct that in
every direct that in every direction in
other words I shall then look in every
possible um direction from here to see
is there any resistance towards anything
else could there be any resistance
towards anything else else so you just
basically expand the same framework
that's already here unchanged
nonresistance yeah if you if you not
resisting that unpleasant feeling you
can't be angry with others
impossible anger towards towards a
person towards something external
requires you to have already jumped on
account of that resistance towards
what's being felt here you're already
averse towards the feeling that you're
feeling and then so how do you tame the
resistance well how do you tame any
craving in regard to any feeling any of
the three types of
feeling ah okay so you want to tame your
real will you need to tame your your your
will you need to tame your your your
desires first cuz that's another way of
jumping on account of what's being felt
just in this sense jumping toward words
jumping with craving jumping with
delight with desire to have more of it
but then when something unpleasant
touches you you jump with the desire to
to get rid of
it I mean the whole the whole practice
of meta it's like one of the uh it's the
Brahma viharas it's the dwelling of the
brahmas and the holy life the celibate
life is called
brahmacharya so you want to dwell like a
Brahma you can't just be having these
well you can think that but if you want
to dwell like a Brahma means your whole
life starts to needs to begin to match
that and You Begin that by practice of
cacy for example even if you have no
instruction about meta and and and and
positive thoughts towards others by
refraining from giving into the physical
desires by refraining from um from
basically desire of sensuality you are
fairing around close to a Brahma like a
Brahma so you want to well like a Brahma
even more so then on account of that
purified livelihood not acting out of lust not
livelihood not acting out of lust not
acting out of aversion taming your mind
taming your senses through a sensory
restraint enduring things rightly and so
on then you can um look closer into like
what's being felt here and now are the
traces of resistance towards that so by
removing the the the resistance towards
an unpleasant feeling here
there will be no external counterpart of
will towards the person out there so
then you just protect that framework
protect it in regard to any direction
anywhere in the world upside down from
wherever it might come the framework
here of non-resistance Remains the Same
you're not sending the
framework to the east north and west no
you protect it here from all these
directions so it's just a way of
describing in the sutas that nowhere up
down below from any direction nothing
can come that can perturb the framework
because the mind has been tained through
establishment in virtue
beforehand so having abandoned
unskillful Behavior this say he then
dwells with the Mind protected with with
friendliness with the framework of
compassion and ultimately with the
framework of equanimity the highest
Brahma Viara is basically the the the equinity
Viara is basically the the the equinity
immovable IND different completely
nothing felt no movement there
whatsoever doesn't matter what comes
from what Direction that's What Brahma
viharas culminate with that's the highest one
culminate with that's the highest one
complete non-existence exactly so you
could already see how your practice of
sending positive
thoughts is incompatible with the
culmination of the that practice of of
of meta if meta were to be sending of
the positive thoughts then surely
practice of indifference would be
sending off indifferent thoughts
spreading indifference towards everyone
how does that work because if if you're
actively engaging with it you're not
indifferent anymore but if it's about protecting of
anymore but if it's about protecting of
the framework then the practice Remains
the Same whether it's the first B of
hara or the
fourth the principle Remains the
Same so that's what that's what I mean
like instead of thinking oh I practice
Brahma Viara by having wishful thinking
and positive thoughts of other people
think that you practice Brahma vihara by
being celibate brahmacharya Brahma vihara and
celibate brahmacharya Brahma vihara and
by being celibate you are taming your
mind which means it's it's even without
actively sort of trying to make it
immovable it's becoming more immovable
in regard to feelings they will want to
move it
otherwise and then sure if you're
already established in all of
that skilled in that behavior then you
could now look even closer into as I
said the the traces of would it move in
regard to this or that are the traces of
are the traces of aversion towards
anything that could be felt towards a
change in the pleasant feeling is there
an aversion is there Delight in in when
when the uh unpleasant feeling
changes and and detach yourself from it
and protect that protect that state of
mind